<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>
      https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-triangle-shirtwaist-factory-fire
    </id>
    <results>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045433/1911-03-26/ed-1/seq-1/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          GIRL EMPLOYES
          LEAP TO DEATH
          FROM WINDOWS
          New York Is Scene of Grewsome Tragedy,
          Due to Insufficient Protection.
          BODIES PILED IN HEAPS ON SIDEWALK
          Blaze Starts On Eighth Floor of Big Building and 800
          Persons are Trapped Eyewitnesses
          Describe Efforts to Escape.
          New York, March 23. Long rows of coffined dead on the shedderl
          morgue pier last so used at the time of the Slocum disaster marked
          the work of a fire in the Asch Building, at Greene street and Washington
          place, late this afternoon.
          There were 133 of the coffins at 11 oclock, and more were coming
          in. Chief Croker estimated the dead at that time at 150, but only 142
          dead had been recovered. Eight died in the hospitals, where seventy
          five wounded had been taken. The dead were shirt-waist makers, mostly
          women and girls, employed by the Triangle Shirt Waist Company, of
          which Max Blanck and Isaac Harris were proprietors. The ten-story
          building, owned by Joseph Asch,
          machines on three of the floors,
          down into a rear courtyard.
          When the fire came, men and women leaped into the street by dozens
          and died there. There were fifty-three corpses on the Greene street side
          walk, w hen the reporters got there. There were more dead -at the bottom
          of the elevator shaft, and many more, some of them burned to mere
          skeletons, on the upper floors.
          The women and girl machine operators who were found dead on the
          street had jumped from the eighth, ninth, and tenth, or top, floors. They
          jumped in groups of twos and threeb into life nets, and their bodies
          spun downward from the high windows of the building so dose to
          gether that the few life nets stretched below soon were broken, and the
          firemen and passers-by who helped hold the nets were crushed to the
          pavement by the rain of falling bodies.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1911-03-26/ed-1/seq-1/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          x carl one hundred and fifty lives were lost in i fire thai swept
          through the *V.-.? upper stories ol a ten stop faet?n lofi building it
          the northwest corner of Washington Place and Greene itreel it ?*
          o clock yesterdai afternoon, occupied bv the Triangle ^v aisl Cotnpan?
          ind a clothing house. \\ mignighl 142 bodies had been taken to the
          morgue,
          ! irr C hief Croker said :
          -This calamity is jusi what 1 have been predicting, fhcre wert
          no outside fire escapes on this building. I \i.c.c been advocating *in?1
          s?ritating that fire escapes h?*- put buildings just ?.ucli as this \Thii
          large loss of life is lue to this neglect.
          ?Thirteen of the victims -.ore men; \29 eye women and girts.
          [he ciiu-c of the fire is unknown. So one has tried r do mort
          than guess at it.
          CROKER BLAMES ESCAPES
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085187/1911-03-27/ed-1/seq-8/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          CRIMINAL ACTION IG
          FOLLOW FIRE HORROR
          (By United Press leased Wire.)
          NEW YORK, March 27. —De-
          claring that 150 loft buildings lv
          Manhattan alone, are In such con
          dition that they might at any time
          furnish a repetition of Saturday's
          fire horror here, District Attor
          ney Whitman today started an in
          vestigation, the result of which,
          It to hoped, will find a remedy for
          the conditions existing.
          'While some officials say that
          the laxity of the law, rather than
          anyone's criminal negligenoe, is
          responsible for the toll of death
          •xacted by the fire in the Asch
          building. Whitman will ask the
          (rand jury to probe the fire fully
          fend if persons have been negligent
          he will demand a prison term for
          them. Assistant Attorney Rubin
          and Bostwlck have been detailed to
          probe the hoiror to the bottom.
          Whitman and his assistants are
          examining 50 witnesses of the hol
          ocaust, including Joßeph Asch,
          owner of the burned building. As
          • possible explanation of th« fire's
          start, it has been learned that the
          employes of the Triangle company
          habitually smoked cigarets and
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1911-03-27/ed-1/seq-1/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          CH3ARETTE CAUSED
          THE FACTORY FIRE
          Croker Finds Stumps and Package That Ex?
          plains Immediate Origin of the Holocaust.
          TRY TO FIX THE RESPONSIBILITY
          Disaster Might Be Repeated Today in Any On? of
          Thousands of Buildings in City, Says Fire
          Chief, Urging Need of Reforms.
          The death list of the factory fir? in V ashington Plac? on >at?ir
          I dav stands at 142. These figure? will be revised only if more ?le.vhs
          I occur in the hospitals.
          A cigarette or a match dropped by a smoker started the fire, b?
          '? *he opinion of * hief Croker.
          Chief Croker said thai Saturday'? disaster might he repeated tr>
          day ? ? iny other day in any ?-?ne
        <?? thousands of buildings in the city.
          11;?- grand jury will probably investigate the ?whole situation ai to
          fire danger in office and lofi buildings. The opinion is general that
          - !.. | ,M ?tself is deficient
          Mayor Gaynot asked the Red Cross to collect tun'!*? fot the relief
          i mfl?er? i s from the fire, and Jacob H. Schiff will receive ??ub??eription$.
          I? seph f. *?sch. ?v ner of the building, denied that a third stairway
          had ever been demanded by the City Department of Buildings.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1911-03-27/ed-1/seq-4/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text> Wl HO? LESSON Insurance Men Think Better Protection Will Come. MIGHT AVERT NEW
          DISASTER Revised Building Laws and Auto raatic Sprinklers Among the Things Demanded.
          ?Man*? ?tending tir" Insurance ?men ?In ihls , ? 11 y vristrrda*. ?ureeil that the
          disaster of S'aturdav nicht iind??iil'??"dl.- W?9UM bring, i),.iiit vartly Improved
          ?SOndttkms In tire , ?protect-On nuch earlier thnn would ?other? ????r have ?baan pnssiPie
          ?Bhrldga <?. ?Snow, ?
          ?,,. .-ddctit r'f the ll.iiiio |n ?iran?e < 'onipany. ,
          I'harlr? ?I. Smith, e??i retary of the Herman?
          Amer lean insurance Conspany, and Theo.I
          lorn H Trie, a former president ?-?f the |
          ITaKK OWTO ?ant-tig ?hose who emphasised
          ?the tact ?hat any ?lay ?flBtghl "ee another :
          nlamitr greater. If anvtMtiK. in it?- hor- ,
          r'?ra. The ii???-c?||y for a lavr nun pell In ir i
          the Installation of automatic aprinkier? in
          all buildings mo?-? i han ?S ?tost i li?l? ?i??- i
          \??'e.i t?? memanlihi ?or ?anuinfMUiilns nur-!
          Sttltl WM imiiileil ?.nt by ?'harles ?; Hriitt M. j
          S mambei of th.? |i?.iil ?if Fir? t"nler*rrlt- |
          er--, and Who has sat Tad "it the Building ?
          Cods ??mmi;;.'?i'?ii sinos Ml
          "??iir hull.linar la?.- ar" .l'fl? iont with r??- i
          ?pe.?? t,, nafSty of life an?! property n?_ain.-t |
          ?.astnwtlan by Btn\m ?said Mr. Smith, "and j
          should b? revised completely ?and made to (
          ?',? ?the prsMnt metii".i? of buttdtng ?on-,
          Itmctkm. 1 belief? ,liat thie '.orrlt'le o\- I
          por!en<~?? i? anipl?* rsaaon tor takinu Imnic- j
          dtate and active ?-step?? for ?tlM adoption of?
          all neeeasary buMlng tpgutatkas having .
          tilt? ??nil in rlew,
          Warninq from Newark Fire.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88078751/1911-03-28/ed-1/seq-1/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          NO OUTSIDE ESCAPES
          Girls Forced to Leap From
          Eighth story Windows.
          EDDIES HORRIBLY MANGLED
          Pier Morgue Filled With Charred
          Remains of Those Unable to
          Escape From Building-Women
          ' Faint In Arms of Nurses as
          L
          Work of Identifing Dead Pro
          gresses. New York, March 27. Conditions
          which ellowed nearly ISO persons to
          fee trapped In a. 10-8tory Jmildins
          when, fire started and proper means
          of escape was lucking, were de
          nounced by architects, city officials,
          state factory inspectors and various
          dric bodies.
          District Attorney "Whitman said:
          "I do not believe that a more im
          portant subject could be put before a
          grand Jury than the Inexcusable con
          ditions that seem to prevail all over
          Manhattan, l'crhaps the laws are
          not drastic enough; possibly such
          laws aro not rigidly enforced; at any
          rata it will -9 essential, I think, for
          tao grand jury to spread oeiore tne
          public the exact situation. If the
          right kind cf laws are lacking; public
          opinion will get them. If the taws
          haven't been enforced, the grand
          Jury may be able to find out who is
          to blame.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1911-03-29/ed-1/seq-1/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text> DOOR IS LOCKED, ANOTHER BLOCKED Survivors, in Affidavit to Build? ings Bureau.
          Confirm Reports Made After Factory Disaster. TELL OF THE EIGHTH FLOOR Only Girl Survivor
          of the Ninth Floor. Deadliest of All. To Be Found, Thinks the Doors There Were Open TELLS
          STORY OF HER ESCAPE Made for Fir?? Escape and Forced Her? self to Go Through Fire and
          Smok? That Poured Out of Eighth Floor Windows-Does Not Romr-mher How She Got Out of Court,
          or How She Reach"?? the Ground The doot to tha ."TaahlrngtOB ri s?**? ??tiirwnv "ti th??
          ?ip'-t'n tt""f of tha As?-h Building waa aocked and * wooden psr titlon ebatructed th? way
          to tha tloraff st tli? Greene atreei stalrwa? according to ,-, sworn atatemeni mad? to tha
          Bureau of Building! yeaternny by Jet?t Ntcoloal of so. MB Ellaabetli ttratt, and ?Roaia
          ?Paaaantino, of ?Vo 12 Mant?n att-aat t*o of the co ig arho ?Nwapcd from tha eighth floor
          ? t ?,"* > * i ? i <if n r: which ooal
            the \ivna r,<- it., nf th??ir ffi1????. awkerra
          Tl ? girl allowed th? ri p-art r hei futa
          which rare bad!) singed snd hei rig t
          hand a hlch raa brrand d ?? th ... .|?i-.
          burn
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085523/1911-03-29/ed-1/seq-6/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          NOT A CHANCE
          FOR THE GIRLS
          Such Appears to Be the Evidence
          of Conditions Surrounding the
          New York Fire
          DOORS SWUNG INWARD
          AND ESCAPES BLOCKED
          Greater Number of the Employes
          Were Unable to Speak English
          Yet There Were No Yiddish or
          Italian Directions
          XEW YORK, March 27. —Fixing the
          blame for tho loss of 142 lives In the
          Washington Square fire Saturday drew
          to a focus the emergency forces of the I
          district attorney's office firs marshal J
          and coroner, stats Isbor department,
          and Borough President McAnnv of
          Manhattan. Dozens of Investigators
          collected available Information and I
          grand jury men turned ths personal
          probers in addition. Tim grand jury
          In formal resolution presented lo the
          court of general ssssions, offereu their
          aid to the district attorney and de
          clared someone should bo prosecuted
          for the disaster.
          Evidence Is Serious
          The investigators found evidence
          that the doors at the exits swung In
          ward, crumpled fire escapes in ths
          air shaft, one fire esctp* blocked by
          the iron shutters when opened in tits
          air shaft, an empty water tank on th.
          roof and the practice prevalent among
          the cutters of lighting cigarettes a
          few minutes before quitting time. All
          of this and what is yet to bo ferretted
          out, will be placed speedily before the
          grand jury.
          Tenement Owners Tried
          The tenement house department
          summoned the owners of half a dozen
          faulty structures to the police court as
          a preliminary step to a far reaching
          investigation of the tenements. Ono
          man was held for violating tho law
          and other cases went over until to
          morrow. Fire Marshal Beeres stated
          today that from his investigations it
          would have required three hours for
          the 700 girl employes to descend by
          one fire escape. There had never been
          a fire drill, nine-tenths of the cm
          i ployes cannot speak English and yet
          j he found no signs in Yiddish or Italian
          pointing to thu exits.
          Illumes a Clguretto
          The fire marshal said he is con
          vinced that a cigarette lit by a cutter
          and thrown into a heap of clippings
          started the fire.
          Thirty-three of the bodies are still
          unidentified. Of theso 133 were taken
          dead from the scene of tho disaster
          and nlno died In hospitals
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88085187/1911-04-04/ed-1/seq-7/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Only Fire Escape New York
          Sweatshop Fire Was a Fire Trap
          ——__—_————»
          This photograph shows the only fire escape on the 10-story
          Ascli building in New York, where 144 persons perished in a sweat
          shop fire in the three upper stories. The Iron shutters on the win
          dows which led to the small, flimsy fire escape opened outward so
          that a girl on the fire escape landing could not reach the fire escape
          without closing the door behind her. Many girls fell from this fire|
          escape and were killed on the pavement eight stories below.
          The picture also shows how the steps leading between the eighth
          and ninth stories collapsed with the weight of a few girls. Students
          of the New York university, who stood during the progress of the
          fire at the very window from which this photograph was taken, de
          clare that none of the girls reached safety from the fire escape,
          which was only a cheap, flimsy contraption, installed to comply
          technically with the law.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045433/1911-04-12/ed-1/seq-1/
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          JDRY INDICTS TWO
          FOR FACTORY FIRE
          Death oi'Ji2 .Brings 1'roprie
          etors" Prosecution.
          New York. April 11 Max Blanck and
          Isaac Harrl-, proprietors of the Trlangl"
          Waist Companv. whoe fictorv at Wash
          ington place was burned out on March
          V. with a los of H- lives wore Indicted
          to-day Th're are two inuirtmonts
          acainbt each of the n en, chirking them
          with first and erond degrre man
          slaughter. The grand jury will on
          tinue Its inquirj and more Indictments
          nnv follow.
          The coroner's jurv did not take anv
          testlmonj, but mot at the scene of the
          disaster nnd carfullv went over tho
          burned building 1 he jurv is made up
          of iron all professionally interested in
          building
          While the jurors were looking over the
          floors they wore met bv the Italian con
          sul, who told them he has been conduct
          ing a separate Inquirj, and has taken the
          affidavits of more than forty Italian glrN
          who escaped Thcc girls tc-tifv to tho
          positions of tie doors on tho ashir.cton
          plaoo sule of the building, and swear
          the -doors wore locked
          On the ninth floor one of tho jurors
          found a portion of a human foot adhering
          to the heel of a shoo, a blood-stained
          waist and skirt.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96088376/1905-08-17/ed-1/?sp=2&q=new+york+factory+fire&;st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1908-05-03/ed-1/?sp=41&q=new+york+factory+fire&;st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014248/1917-11-13/ed-1/?sp=11&q=new+york+factory+fire+triangle&;st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053292/1912-01-04/ed-1/?sp=5&q=factory%2C+fire%2C+isaac+harris%2C+max+blanck%2C+new+york%2C+shirtwaist%2C+triangle+fire%2C+triangle+waist+company&st=text&r=-0.217,0,1.435,1.435,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          FACTORY OWNERS STILL LIABLE
          Proprietors of Burned Shirtwaist Fac
          tory May Face Second Trial.
          New York.-There is every indication
          that Isaac Harris and Max Blanck, pro
          prietors of the Triangle Waist com
          pany, in whose factory 147 lives were
          lost during a fire on March 25, will
          be placed on trial again.
          They were acquitted in the first trial,
          on an indictment charging manslaugh
          ter.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90062374/1911-03-29/ed-1/?sp=8&q=factory%2C+fire%2C+isaac+harris%2C+max+blanck%2C+new+york%2C+shirtwaist%2C+triangle+fire%2C+triangle+waist+company&st=text&r=-0.184,0,1.368,1.368,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          MOSTLY EAST SIDE GIRLS
          Fire in Top of Ten-Story Building
          A
          i Occupied as Shirtwaist Factory—
          Many of the Victims Jumped from
          1 Windows, Others Smothered or
          Burned to a Crisp.
          NEW YORK, March 28.—Ome hundred
          and fifty people, nine-tenths of them girls
          from the East Side, were crushed to death
          on the pavements, smothered in smoke
          or shrivelled crisp yesterday afternoon in
          the worst fire New York has known since
          the steamship General Slocum was burn
          ed to the water’'s edge off North Brothers
          island in 1904.
          Nearly all, if not all, of the victims
          were employed by the Triangle Shirtwalist
          company on the eighth, ninth and tenth
          floors of the ten-story lof.t building at 23
          Washington place, on the western fringe
          of the downtown wholesale clothing, fur
          sand millinery district. The owners of
          the company, Isaac Harris and Max
          Blanck, escaped unscathed from the office
          -on -the tenth floor, carrying with them
          over an adjoining roof Blanck’'s two
          yvoung daughters and a governess. There
          ‘was not an outside fire escape on the
          building.
          How the fire started will perhaps never
          "be known. A corner on the eighth floor
          was its point of origin, and the three
          ~upper floors only were swept. On the
          'ninth floor fifty bodies were found, sixty
          three or more were crushed to death by
          jumping and more than thirty clogged
          the elevator shafts. The loss to property
          will not exceed SIOO,OOO.
          Pedestrians going home through Wash
          ington place to Washington square at
          ten minutes to 5 were scattered by the
          whiz of something rushing through the
          air before them. There was a flop on the
          pavement and a body flattened on the
          flags. Wayfarers on the opposite side
          of the street shaded their eyes against
          the setting sun- and saw the windows of
          the three upper floors of the building
          black with girls crowding to the sills.
          There were no fire escapes.
          “Don’t jump, don’t jump!” yelled the
          crowd. But the girls had no choice. The
          pressure of the maddened hundreds be
          hind them and the urging of their own
          fears were too strong.
          Four alarms were rung within fifteen
          minutes. Before the engines could re
          spond, before the nets could be stretched
          or the ladders raised five girls had fallen
          from the eighth and ninth floors so heav
          ily that the broke through the iron roofs
          of the sub-cellar and crashed through the
          very streets into the vaults below.
          NEW YORK, March 26.—Robert. W. De-
          Forest announced tonight that the New
          York chapter of the National Red Cross
          would collect funds for the relief of the
          survivors of the “’ashin%}on square fire
          and that Mayor Gaynor had headed the
          contributions with SIOO. A call for funds
          has been issued by Mayor Gaynor.
          ter.
        </text>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>

  <topic>
    <id>
      https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-olympics
    </id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1960-02-07/ed-1/?sp=136&st=text&r=-0.185,-0.069,1.371,1.371,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Daring young girl on the flying skis! In slalom.
          Linda must swerve with split-second timing between poles
          28 Keep
          In next week’s big Olympic
          ski races, watch Linda Meyers.
          She’s an All-American beauty
          and a downhill daredevil
          Squaw Valley, Calif.
          Girl skiers, as any male skier will tell you, are
          the prettiest athletes around. No exceptions
          are the members of Uncle Sam’s Olympic
          women's ski team, going into action against the
          world’s best in the upcoming winter Olympics
          at Squaw Valley. Shown here, for example, is
          happy, outgoing, 22-year-old Linda Meyers, as
          attractive a girl as you’d care to meet coming
          down any mountainside.
          Linda is one of Uncle Sam’s best bets for a
          gold medal in the big meet starting next week.
          Behind her spectacular rise to a top place
          among America’s girl skiers lies a drama
          involving a bribe, a tragedy and a bright idea.
          The "bribe” went to Dave McCoy, Linda's
          high-school coach at Bishop, Calif., and her
          biggest rooter today. McCoy, who has taught
          a dozen stars the tricks of the ski trade, just
          didn’t think Linda would ever amount to much
          as a skier. "She had hardly any natural
          talent,” he says candidly. "She certainly
          wasn’t graceful. I told her I didn’t see any
          4te 11/ iI, I w
          F'ed I yon
          Protty pupil: Linda with coach Date McCoy
          THIS WEEK Magazine February 7, 1960
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1960-02-19/ed-1/?sp=63&q=olympics&st=text&r=-0.37,-0.087,1.739,1.739,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Athletes Open Action
          In Winter Olympics
          B
          SQUAW VALLEY. Calif.. Feb
          t 19 (AP).—The eighth Winter
          t Olympic Games get down to
          j business today. The athletes
          take over and start gunning
          for the precious gold, silver and
          I bronze medals.
          And judging by the moving i
          and dignified opening day
          ceremonies—which drew raves
          from almost everyone here
          1 from home and abroad—this,
          still could be a magnificent
          show if the weatherman co- i
          operates.
          I The prediction for competi-
          J tion starting at 11 am. 'Wash
          ington time' and running
          through the afternoon-and-
          night hockey games was for
          partly cloudy weather with a
          high temperature of 40 in mid-
          day.
          48 Skiers Entered
          r The Scandinavians were ex
          pected to dominate the first
          event, the men's 30-kilometer
          (18 64 miles) cross-country ski
          race scheduled for 11 a.m.
          Forty eight long distance
          skiers were entered in the
          cross-country at McKinney
          Creek, 17 miles from here.
          I i This, however, figured to be
          D-1
          a battle among Finland's Veikko
          Hakulinen, the defending cham
          pion; Sixten Jernberg, Swe
          den’s “king of the skis”; Nor
          way's Hallgeir Brenden, and
          Kalevi Hamalainen, another
          veteran Finnish ace. Russia’s
          crack Pavel Kolchin was with
          drawn because of illness. He
          had a cold and was running a
          temperature.
          The United States, as usual,
          wasn't given a chance for a
          medal in this grind. Uncle Sam's
          I entries include Leo Massa,
          Lake Placid. N. Y.; Mack Mil
          ler, Crested Butte. Colo.; Sven
          Johanson. Spenard, Alaska, and
          Joe Pete Wilson, Lake Placid,
          N. Y.
          The spectacular Canadian
          team of Bob Paul and Barbara
          (Wagner was the experts’ pick
          |in the pairs figure skating set
          Ito open at 1:30 p m. in the $3.5
          million Blyth Ice Palace.
          Organizers Heartened
          These were the only cham
          pionships on tap following the
          postponement of the men's
          downhill race to February 22
          because of yesterday's heavy
          snowfall.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1960-02-29/ed-1/?sp=18&q=olympics&st=text&r=-0.383,-0.088,1.765,1.765,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Hockey Victory Caps r
          Successful Olympics
          SQUAW VALLEY. Calif.,c
          Feb. 29 (AP).—America’s Cin-
          derella hockey team, the club
          they said couldn’t win but did.
          provided the climax for the
          B Winter Olympic Games that
          1 opened amid criticism and
          closed with high praise.
          s Coach Jack Riley’s Yankees
          won the first hockey Gold
          Medal in this Nation's history
          yesterday by staging a third
          t period comeback for six goals
          i and a 9-4 victory over Czecho-
          Slovakia after trailing. 4-3.
          s That rally brought the
          United States its third Gold
          Medal of the games and a
          third-place finish behind Rus
          sia and Sweden. The Swedes
          t were just one-half point ahead
          •I of the United States in the
          !i unofficial standings, with Ger
          many another half point be
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016244/1956-11-26/ed-1/?sp=7&q=olympic&st=text&r=-0.278,-0.078,1.556,1.556,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          U. S. Athletes Pile Up Olympic Medals
          By TED SMITS
          MELBOURNE M A superhu
          man effort by Tom Courtney in
          the 800 meter run and an amaz
          ing pole vault by the Rev. Bob
          Richards gave the United States
          two more gold medals in track
          and field today and Denmark's
          Emil Denielsen speared a new
          world’s record in the ja- ~’in.
          Yale’s comeback eight and
          Jack Kelly Jr. led a parade of six
          American rowing entries into
          Tuesday’s finals and the Ameri
          can weight lifter moved every
          thing but the Olympic Stadium.
          Bobby Morrow, gunning for a
          100-200-m3534 “double” breezed
          through two heats into the semi
          finals along with teammates
          Thane Baker of Elkhart, Kan.,
          and Andy Stanfield the 2
          champ from Jersey City, N. J.
          Although Morrow, the flash from
          Abilene Christian College pulled
          a thigh muscle, he is expected to
          be all right for tomorrow’s races.
          Failure of Cy Young to repeat in
          the javelin toss was a major dis
          appointment to the American
          team after the giant rancher from
          Modesto, Calif., had broken the
          Olympic mark in the qualifying
          round.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1956-12-06/ed-1/?sp=65&q=olympics+water+polo&st=text&r=-0.337,-0.084,1.674,1.674,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          HEAD-ON COLLISION AT OLYMPICS—Ervin Zador (left), Hungarian water
          polo team member, is led from the Olympic pool in Melbourne after suffering
          a cut from a head butting by a Russian opponent in rough Olympic water polo
          finals. The match was cut short as a result of the incident. The crowd booed
          the Soviet players. The Russian team was a 4-0 loser.—AP Wirephoto via radio
          from Melbourne.
          WIN LOSE OR
          DRAW By FRANCIS STANN
          This Was Goldie's Night
          If’ NOT ALL OF THE PROS were present, there were
          enough to properly honor Goldie Ahearn at the Statler. The
          International Boxing Club sent down a contingent, mostly
          guys who'd just seen and who have an interest in Floyd
          Patterson, kayo winner over Archie Moore.
          Harry Markson, the managing director, was on hand and
          so was Murray Goodman, who makes with the words. "We
          never Jhad it so good,” Markson was saying. "This kid Pat
          terson has the fastest pair of hands I’ve ever seen for a
          hatvy weight."
          ‘T’ll buy it,” Goodman was saying in Jim Magner’s suite.
          "There’s a whole new deal in the heavyweight division, w’hich
          is what you’ve got to have if boxing is going to be any good
          at all. We’ve got Patterson, No. 1. He’s 21 years old. Back
          of him we’ve got Eddie Machen, who is only 23.”
          “Twenty-four,” Markson said, tentatively.
          "I looked it up, boss,” Murray said. “Be’a 23, just going
          on 24.”
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016244/1956-12-07/ed-1/?sp=11&q=olympic&st=text&r=-0.256,-0.076,1.512,1.512,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Diving Double
          Nets US Sweep
          By TED SMITS
          MELBOURNE W Mre. Pat
          McCormack scored an unprece
          dented Olympic diving “double
          double" tonight when she led a
          1-2-3 American sweep in the plat
          form dive after Murray Rose and
          Lorraine Crapp, two Australian
          teen agers, dominated the final
          night's swimming races.
          Mrs. McCormack, who won both
          the springboard and platform dive
          crowns at Helsinki in 1952, repeat
          ed her double victory. Mrs. Juno
          Stover Irwin of Glendale, Calif.,
          waas second and Paula Jean Myers
          a Southern California coed from
          Glendora, Calif., was third.
          The best Uncle Sam’s men and
          women swimmers could do was
          third place in the final races as
          Rose took the men's 1,500-meter
          free style and Miss Crapp grab
          bed the women’s 400-meter free
          style in record time.
          Despite the diving sweep and
          the brilliant performance by Mrs.
          McCormick, a Lakewood, Calif.,
          housewife and mother, the United
          States could make little inroad into
          Russia’s bulging point total.
          The Russians had already
          clinched the unofficial champion
          ship with a great demonstration
          of strength in gymnastics and
          wrestling. All that remained on
          the Olympic program was tomor
          row’s final soccer game, in which
          Russia is a finalist, and the clos
          ing ceremonies.
          While the athletes were com
          peting before another sellout
          crowd of 5.500 in the Olympic
          pool, several members of the
          Hungarian team were making
          the fateful decision between re-
          turning to their revolution-torn
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1956-12-10/ed-1/?sp=20&q=olympics&st=text&r=-0.339,-0.084,1.679,1.679,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Olympic athletes and officials
          from 68 nations today continued
          the rush from Australia back to
          a world of reality which has its
          eyes focused on Suez—not swim
          ming—and Hungary, not hur
          dling.
          Eor them a dream is at an end.
          Their time-consuming efforts,
          which produced four new' world
          records in track and field and
          a host of records in other Olym
          pic sports, will be all but for
          gotten until sportsmen and spec
          tators gather again at Rome in
          four years’ time.
          An Australian band broke
          Melbourne’s quiet Sunday spell,
          marching tin the main thorough
          fare playing ’’Waltzing Matilda.”
          With the passing strains went
          the proud Aussies’ apparent
          recognition that their dream and
          accomplishment —an Olympics
          Down Under—was fast fading
          into the past. All the hopes, frus
          trations and struggles which
          went into making the Games
          perhaps the most successful of
          all time were filed into history
          with the athletic achievements.
          The Games opened nearly
          three weeks ago on a joyous
          note as the athletes happily
          marched into the vast Melbourne
          cricket grounds behind the ban
          ners of their countries. But also
          who could forget the gallant
          Hungarian water polo team as it
          stood on the victory dais on the
          eve of the games’ closing, singing
          with tears in their eyes, their
          pre-Communist national an
          them, “God Save Hungary”?
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1952-07-19/ed-1/?sp=10&q=olympic&st=text&r=-0.289,-0.079,1.579,1.579,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          HELSINKI. July 19.—The Pres
          ident of the Republic of Finland,
          before 70,000 rain-soaked spec
          tators, today opened the 15th
          Olympic Games, the biggest in
          history and the first to be attend
          ed by Soviet Russia.
          President Juho K. Paasikivi
          and two Olympic officials wore
          formal clothes, the only ones to
          hold to custom on this solemn,
          but sodden occasion.
          As the band played the presi
          dential salute the trio walked
          down the line of the International
          Olympic Committee, shaking
          hands in the downpour.
          Only about half of the Olympic
          officials even bothered to wear
          raincoats. The Finnish Olympic
          Committee stuck to its gray suits.
          Despite the rain, which started
          about an hour before the games
          opened, the Btands were practi
          cally full. Only one side of the
          modernistic stadium is covered.
          Olympic Slogans Flashed.
          After greeting the Olympic of
          ficials, Paasikivi took his seat in
          the President’s box.
          The parade of the 5,870 athletes
          from 69 nations taking part in
          the games followed the alphabeti
          cal order in Finnish, except that
          Greece, as always, came first.
          Finland came last as the home
          team.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016244/1952-07-23/ed-1/?sp=6&q=olympic&r=0.109%2C0.139%2C0.76%2C0.662%2C0&st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Record Breaking
          Olympic Carnes
          HELSINKI wv—A duel between
          the United States and Russia for
          the victors’ gold medals developed
          today as the fourth day of com
          petition in the 15th Olympic Games
          produced a series of record-smash
          ing performances even greater
          than those of the first three days.
          One world record was smashed,
          anther equalled and five new
          Oiympic marks were written into
          the books in the track and field
          competition, still unfinished.
          Russia took two gold medals in
          wrestling and another in rowing
          as Turij Tjukalov dethroned Aus
          tralia’s defending Champion Mer
          vyn Wood in the gruelling single
          sculls rowing event.
          And the United States scored its
          first victory in Olympic history in
          the pair without coxswain rowing
          when Chuck Logg Jr., son of the
          Rutgers University coach, and
          Tom Price came home in the final
          ahead of Belgium’s pair.
          Adhemar Ferriera da Silva of
          Brazil turned in the most remark
          able of the record-breaking track
          and field performances when he
          surpassed his own listed world rec
          ord on four successive attempts
          in the hop, step and jump. His
          third and winning effort was 16.22
          meters (53 feet, 2.59 inches), about
          eight inches over his own listed
          world mark.
          Two Americans participated in
          the track record breaking and an
          other equalled the Olympic stand
          ard.
          Horacre Ashenfelter, the Glen
          Ridge, N. J., FBI man, won his
          trial heat in the 3,000-meter stee
          plechase in eight minutes, 51 sec
          onds. There is no official world
          record for this event of about a
          mile and three-quarters over ob
          stacles, but Ashenfelter was near
          ly 13 seconds under the Olympic
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88063132/1952-08-04/ed-1/?sp=5&q=olympic&st=text&r=-0.206,-0.071,1.411,1.411,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Yanks Win Championship In Final Rounds Os Olympic Games
          U. S Wins Title
          By 614 Points
          To Russia’s 553
          By Leo H. Petersen
          9 (United Press Sports Editor)
          HELSINKI (IP) The tumult
          and the shouting died today and
          the fifteenth Olympic games of
          modern times went into the history
          book—an unequalled carnival of
          record-breaking featured by Amer
          ica’s inspired uphill climb to the
          team championship.
          All that remained today was for
          the weary athletes to bid farewell
          to their new friends from other
          #uations and to begin their trek back
          to their homes all over the world.
          And they could all proudly re
          flect that they were part of per
          haps the most fantastic sports
          show of all time, the Slow that
          saw Russia emerge from hahfr,-:
          the Iron Curtain and almost, but
          not quite, beat the U. S. for the
          team title, and the show that saw
          world and Olympic records broken
          176 times in track and field alone.
          The Soviets’ appearance for the
          ■irst time since 1912 was, of course,
          the biggest thing at these games
          which were formally concluded
          yesterday amid colorful pageantry.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1963-12-15/ed-1/?sp=74&q=olympic+games&r=-0.167,0.863,0.932,0.705,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025327/1963-12-11/ed-1/?sp=16&q=olympic+games&r=-0.066,0.915,0.95,0.719,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1963-12-13/ed-1/?sp=66&q=olympic+games&r=-0.289%2C0.263%2C1.407%2C1.065%2C0&st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Miss Saubert, 21, considered
          America's best hope for a Gold
          Medal at the Winter Olympic
          Games, flashed through the 66
          gates on the 1.600-meter course
          on the Bellevade slope with a
          drop of 340 meters in 2:01.40
          Therese Obrecht of Switzer
          land captured second place
          with a run of 2:02.20
          Marielle Goitschel, a native
          of Vai D’lsere, was thud In
          2:03.63. Annie Famose of
          France, winner of the women's
          special slalom yesterday, was
          fourth in 2:05.38, and Christine
          Goltschel, Martelle’s sister, was
          fifth with 2:06.10.
          The victory would give Miss
          Saubert a combined champion
          ship for the two slalom events
          as well. She finished only four
          tenths of a second behind the
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83007243/1958-12-12/ed-1/?sp=6&q=olympic&st=text&r=-0.33,-0.083,1.661,1.661,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          The event is known as the Olympic games.
          The first Olympic champion was Coroebus of
          ills. He outfooted a squad of 200-yard dashmen in
          i great foot race staged in a meadow beside the
          river Alpheus at Olympia in 776 B.CV
          It took exactly 1170 years of competition, bicker
          ing (sound familiar), conniving and ill will before
          Emperor Theodosius I of Rome called off the athletic
          carnival in 394 A. D., to prevent the spread of fur
          ther dissension among tne stalwarts of the then
          known world.
          The next Olympic champion was not crowned
          until 1896 when a Boston Irishman, a Catholic, won
          the initial event in the opening of the "modern Olym
          pics."
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86069180/1916-07-22/ed-1/?sp=4&q=olympics&st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>

  <topic>
    <id>
      https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-radium
    </id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-04-19/ed-1/?sp=36&q=Joint+Discoverers+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Radium+Metal&st=text&r=-0.317,-0.082,1.634,1.634,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text> A WONDERFUL WOMAN AND HER HUSBAND WHO ARE JOINT DISCOVERERS OF A WONDERFUL METAL
          -RADIIM PROFESSOB AND MME. CURIE AND DAUGHTER SEATED IX THEIR GARDEN (Photograph by Hurry
          C Ellis, Paris.) ably bo beaten in the vicinity of the Pouth P< le ,
            which is believed to be surrounded by land. No
            such severe cold has been found on Arctic seas,
            iven in the highest latitude reached. By un
            hianned balloons Bent up last winter in Europe
            a temperature of 87 below zero was recorded.
            With this preface one can partially under
            stand a communication recently published in
          "The Monthly Weather Review" and "The Na
          tional Geographic Magazine." both <>f Washing ton. R. C.
          Mossman, meteorologist of the Scot tish Antarctic expedition, now exploring the re gion
          southeastward of Cape Horn, mentions his preparations for sending up instruments wit>,
          kilos, but adds: "There is some possibility of losing a record by the freezing of the ink,
          as we have not tin newly Invented ink containing tonsol." As to what "tonsol" is the
          dictionaries do not tell. Mr. Mossman is at present inaccessible. Leading chemists in the
          metropolis have never heard <>f it; and this is the waj in which Pro fessor Willis 1..
          Moore, chief of the United States Weather Bureau in Washington, answers a query concerning
          it We regret th.it there has been .some delay in making this reply, occasioned by our
          efforts to ascertain, if possible, some particulars con cerning the substance "tonsoL" The
          only in formation in the possession of the Weather Bureau concerning the particular ink
          mentioned in Mr Mossman's letter is that con tained in the letter itself. An Inquiry of
          chem ical experts and a search for references to the substance "tonsol" fail to develop
          any further particulars. Dr. Wiley, chief chemist of the Department of Agriculture,
          informs u.s that in very old climates it is customary to add a cer tain portion of
          glyc«rol or calcium chloride to rtiks to secure fluidity, and it i.s possible the term
          •"tonsol" may be a trade name for some of these todies. RADIUM DISCOVERERS. Professor and
          Mme. Curie Are In deed Helpmeets. Paris, April 10. The most striking and interesting
          personages It ill' present moment in Paris are Professor Pierre Curie and his wife, his
          Invaluable co «their lives to an astonishingly brilliant series of experiments in the
          extraction and isolation 01 radium, the most mysterious and most costly metal kntwn to the
          scientific world. M. and Mme. Curie have provided science with a new and most powerful
          weapon. The mineral, which ha* become the great talk of the day, was dis covered in 1898
          by If. and Mme. Curie, who, after long and complicated chemical researches, succeeded in
          extracting from a ton of the pitch blende mineral of Joachinistal, in Bohemia, two
          decigrams of radium. The operation cost over which is at the rate of $10.1100 a gram, or
          $10,000,000 a kilogram. To borrow ihe definition <>f Sir William Crook* s radium possesses
          the "extraordinary proportj continuously emitting heat without combustion, without
          r-hemical change of any kitpl anit without anj rhang* 3 in its molecular structure, which
          remains spectroscoplcally Hl'ii:. 1 aftPi- many months of continuous i,i--i. n Radium salt
          emits, without r- pi ii'i< diminutioi of its own •i i l'' i'\
          NEW YORK TRIBUNE ILLUSTRATED^SUPPLEMENT.
          sufficient heat to melt more than its own weight j
          of ice every hour. Radium en. its r,i\s of its own
          which have the qualities of X rays and of
          cat hod ie rays, and is as active in vacuum as in
          air. Uranium and thorium throw off analogous
          rays, but of an intensity a millionfold less than
          the radium rays. The rays "i emanations from
          radium penetrate through certain opaque bodies
          and make impressions on sensitive films m
          closed wooden boxes. For instance, if a coin or
          a key or other object be placed in a leather
          purse and the purse put ii ' he dark on a sensi
            tive plate, and a little radium be placed near at
            hand, it will be found that the development of
            the plate will produi c photographs of the coin or
            key, just as is the case with the Rontgen rays.
            The radiations of radium rea< I chemically upon
            certain bodies; for instance, they transform
            oxygen into ozone, and they change the colors of
            glass or porcelain t.. dark violet or brown.
            Another extraordinary property of radium is i
            to throw off rays not only of heat, but of light
            like those of the plow worm or firefly. Indeed, j
            th*» li^ht rays of radium are so powerful that it
            has been suggested liy French scientists that in
            this mysterious metal may some day lie found a
            means of lighting cities without loss of energy
            or waste of force. The rays radium dash and
            explode like minute artillery projectiles upon
            sensitive surfaces, and '.heir phosphorescent
          properties are astounding. The most puzzling
          property of radium is that, as far as has yet
          been ascertained, it.- properties of emit) heat
          and light are inexhaustible. The great Mys
          tery is how and where the ambient forces
          needed to produce heat and light are absorbed
          by radium. According to the laws of the con
          servat' on and correlation of forces, heat, light
            end motion are convertible, and neither Profes
            «or nor Mine. Curie, nor Sit William Crookes,
            nor any of the scientists of France. England or
            Germany who have followed in Professor Curie's
          footsteps, have yet been able to prove that the
          incessant continuity in the emission of rays of
          light and heat from radium causes any exhaus
          tion, expenditure or diminution of the prop
          PROFESSOR AND MMI CURIE AND DAUGHTER.
          AViilking in their garden in front of their little cottage at inilly. Fr?n.«»
          (Photograph by Harry C. Ellis, Parls.J
          erties bo mysteriously stored In apparently fcj,
          finite quantities in tail extraordinary metal.
          Radium, rr»>r' - has startling effects cpai
            the nervous centres of hum;;n being?) and ..-,!nf
          animal.". A glass tube containing one or fsij
          milligrams of radium \*h'-r. carried f n tha
          waistcoat pocket causes a painful wound in tile
          flesh that will require six month- Jo heal. A
          glass tut"'- containing a few mfllisrrairs
          radium when introduced beneath the skin «s? a
          mouse near the vertebral column produced «!»at&
          by paralysis in three hour*. Tut^s of r^uia
          placed in contact with the back of the nerks ef
          guinea pigs kill or paralyze the animals ta a
          few hours, according to th« length »,f *jpoto its fatal radiations. M Curie say? that d^ari
          to man would probably ensue upon '•nfrin? a
          room containing a pound of radium, liaf'mm is,
          indeed, an unknown quantity. F^nh we***
          brings to light startling addition to its mjs
          terious properties, which, as far as i* ;-»-t known,
          emanate and originate in itself, and nu-e sci
          entists to ask the rjuestiosi. "Can it (XMtsltli
          that Professor and Mn»*\ Curie have i<. r.i.ttas!
          discovered perpetual motion?
          Professor Pierre Curie, whom it ha.s be«-n my
          good fortune to meet on several a?:or.s, bod
          at his little cottage, near tlentniy, and In xtt
          laboratories of the>'orbonr.<>, v. her- h* work*. ;j a man of
          impressive individuality. Th<-re is
          Irresistible, fascination in he soft bat pene
          trating gTance Oi bis large hazel whicll
          seem to emit rays of intelligence akin to those
          of the mysterious metal which he and his tal
          ented wife have di?:overed. M. Curi-i is forty
          years old, tall and well formed. He with the artistic negligence that is often char
          acteristic of men of genius. His beard and hair
          are luxuriant, and his placid e.xpr-.5.-;kn of
          beatitude, together with the pure antique lines
          of his head and face, suggest the portraits oJ
          Christ as depicted in the paintings of Albert
          Diirer. Professor Curi^ disdains worldrj mat
          ters and lives high up in th-i clouds, rapt is
          the of his mystic radium.
          He and hLs wife are by no mear.s in ,;f!2j*r.t
          circumstances. Th-y live in a small ottage
          with a green lawn and fruit tr^es in the most
          inaccessible southern district of Paris, over
          looking the fortifications, far away from the
          I^itin Quarter, and also a long distance froa
          the. intellectual and fashionable centra of tie
          capital. Professor Curie is an early riser. At i
          o'clock in the morning, ufrer having given hi 3
          little daughter a lesson ta arithmetic, h^ jurr.fa
          on his hieyele and pedals briskly thre* miles to
          the l;\borator>' of the Sorbonr.^. in the Ku* Cuvier, near the Jardin dcs
          Plant-, to t!:« laboratory of the Kcole de Physi-iue. i:i th« Rue T-honiand, behind the
          Pantheon. It was the Fatter laboratory' that Profet^.jr Curie ft- M le fore me a small
          glass test tub- containing a gra>lsb white powder resemi'lhig table said. "You see. this
          is radium:' The pri.fVssflr, :o illustrate the fact that carrying radiurr. about produces
          flesh burns or wounds, good nat ;r<«li7
          bared his left arm arid showed me a d^*p *"unJ
          that had been four months healing-.
          The professor i- extremely fond of hi* little
          cottage, with lawn and fruit trf-e= and ki?> h»S garden. It was in his little garden that re ceived
          me last Sunday, and presented me to his</text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1903-07-19/ed-1/?sp=37&q=Radium+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Metal+Universal+Light+Bringer+Blind&st=text&r=-0.25,-0.075,1.501,1.501,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Doctor London placed a box of radium behind a screen and the blind child Bprang excitedly
          toward it.
          He could see the light.
          Bptdal Correeponlesee ef The Euno&y Republic
          St. Petersburg. June SO. I made a blind
          boy see by means of radium, and the fact
          Justifies a detailed discussion of the new
          element's properties and the hope It holds
          out to suffering mankind.
          The radium preparation placed at my dis
          posal for experimental purposes looked, at
          first Eight, Ilka a bit of ground tobacco,
          resembling tho same In substance, and
          color.
          After I had satisfied myself to that effect,
          my assistant, a chemist, asked permission
          to plato a black bandago o er my eyes.
          I -wore the same live or seven minutes,
          when he came tow ard me with, a small box
          containing tho ery radium I had creiously
          examined.
          Holding the box before my cohered eyes
          at a distance of from four to six and one
          half Inches, tho following sensations mani
          fested themselves:
          My blind-folded right eye had a distinct
          perception ot light, growing stronger as
          tny assistant advanced upon me, at cen
          timeter stages. (Three centimeters equal to
          ens Inch.)
          It seemed as It my right eye had entered
          Into a light Ephere. yet there were no sharp
          pontours or outlines.
          J'ei.t tho boxed radium was advanced
          toward jnS left eye, which up to then had
          but scantily profiled by Uie Ught-brlnger
          ''and Immediately following the light eensa-
          j Hon in my right ee became dim. while that
          in my left materially Increased.
          I asked tho assistant to place the radium,
          paste-board cover and olL into a. small
          metal match box, whereupon the experi
          ments were renewed, the result being al
          most similar. The light sphere observed
          was but a shade less bright.
          Then I placed my hand oor the blind
          folded e e and saw as much as before.
          Two friends put their hands over mine.
          Result the game.
          Here, then, was a light-bearer for the
          more or less sightless, tho degree being
          hardly of any consequence.
          Still blindfolded, I asked my assistant to
          point the radium toward my forehead.
          Then, too. I perceived the light sensation
          described: that is. I saw tho radium rays,
          not the boxes holding them prisoner.
          Some time later a friend called, who has
          a peculiar, nervous head.
          Wo held the box several Inches away
          from the back of his head, his eyss being
          blindfolded. According to his description he
          experienced the same light sensations that
          had astonished me.
          At tho time of writing the above experi
          ments have been tried on a dozen or more
          reliable men and women, with the results
          j' noted.
          STARTLING DISCOVERIES
          HADE IX DARK ROOM.
          We next experimented In a dark room,
          dispensing, ot course, with the blindfolding
          business.
          As expected, the same results were had.
          Still later a person possessed of one sound
          tni one unsound eye was experimented
          with. It developed that the light Impres
          sions conveyed by radium on the sound eye
          'i'iiI'
          ill
          were stronger than those on the other.
          The left eye of another young person In
          vestigated Is minus a retina. The radium
          rays made no impression whatever on that
          eye.
          Every optician will tell the reader that a
          perfect crystaUIne lens Is necessary to In
          sure good sight. Our experiments fIiow that
          a good, healthy crystalline lens diminishes
          the Impressions of radium rays on the eye.
          It seems to repel them.
          The question arose: Can a blindfolded
          person, or a person In a dark room, per
          ceh o articles on which radium ra a are re
          flected? Experiments proved that such Is Impossi
          ble, for radium rays penetrate the article,
          and. In part, ore swallowed up by It.
          With respect to the experiment of holding
          radium above the line of the eye. It was ob
          served that the lower half of the retina
          caught the rays; myself and others had
          been under the impression that the light
          came from above.
          We did not know the assistant's position
          till later.
          We continued experiments In the way that
          tho assistant described, with his radium
          box, various flgureB, representing numbers,
          letters, diagrams and words before tho
          blindfolded persons. All these figures were
          Instantly recognized. This latter fact still
          more strengthened my belief that radium
          may he placed in the service of the blind
          with most beneficial results.
          With this end In view I thought at first
          of playing tho radium raj son tho retina di
          rect, but that was an error of theory as
          well as practice, for, in the first place, not
          one retina of sightless persons resembles the
          other, and. again, radium rays play havoc
          with living tissues. 8o we were forced to
          resort to mechanical apparatus.
          LIGHT COULD RE INTENSIFIED
          OR DIMINISHED.
          To this end we tmployed barlum-platln
          cjanlde, and holding sime at a certain dis
          tance from the box with radium saw It light
          up with subdued yellowish-green fluores
          cence, the peculiar appearance presented by
          certain substances on being viewed by re
          flected light.
          The light, moreover, could be Intensified or
          diminished by moving tho radium box near
          er or farther away.
          To the apparatus, figures, writing, dia
          grams, eta, may be attached, and after It Is
          lit up by radium, tho blind can perceive the
          meaning cr characters, the only condition
          being that the attachments are of nontrans
          parent material, black paper, lead, etc.
          Our experiments further show that under
          such conditions the sightless eye Is easily
          educated.
          Remember, though, there must be no side
          lights, none other but the fluorescence.
          The principle, let me add. Is not new. It
          Is the same that enables us to' see the stars
          at night, and to see them the better the
          darker It Is.
          Next w txpertmented with a box of ra
          dium placed behind the screen, with the re
          sult that on the opposite side an intense
          light spot appeared.
          The several blind people, under my. obser
          THE REPUBLIC: SUNDAY. JULY 19. 1003.
          r
          foffsd
          vation wero able to perceive that spot and
          to follow its movements. The radium box
          described a circle behind the screen and
          the blind man Imitated the same with a pen
          cil on a sheet of paper.
          Letters and whole words were convoyed
          to those previously educated In schools for
          the blind in the same way.
          I therefore maintain that It will be pos
          slblo to teach the blind to read and write
          by way of radium, also to draw figures,
          etc.
          Among others I Introduced an 11-year-old
          boy to the new method.
          In tho first )ear of his life this boy had
          become blind, owing to an affectation of
          both nerves of vision.
          Tet his eies were still capable of receiv
          ing a certain amount of light Impressions!
          he can distinguish between light and dark
          ness BLIND BOX LEARNED TO READ.
          After a week of experimenting the blind
          boj learned to make out letters that were
          radlumgraphed on the screen.
          The letters wero about three Inches high
          and some three Inches apart.
          To-day my little pupil can read words
          composed of letters.
          That much demonstrated, tho physiologic
          al aspects ot radium Ehould be examined.
          According to my own observations. Its
          Impress on organisms has three different
          periods
          The first Is more or less latent, at least
          I could perceive of no visible changes.
          During the necond period the organisms
          teem to be In a sort ot Inflamed state, not
          always patent to the eye, yet requiring
          close examination.
          Tho third period Is that ot destruction
          more or less farreachlng, according to the
          Intensity of the radium-rays employed.
          This Indicates that radium-rajs, when we
          completely understand them, will lend
          themselves to Various medical purposes In
          asmuch as a gradual scale of exposure may
          be established, the result depending upon
          time and tho quantity and quality of the
          radium used.
          Furthermore, I ascertained that the In
          fluence of radium rays on organisms de
          pends. In a large measure, on the natuse of
          things coming In contact with the metal.
          I have not Vet found a thing, organism
          or object that Is not. In some way. Influ
          enced by an exposure to radium ras. Our
          experiments embraced Seed, bacteria, cells
          of animal eggs, frogs-spawn, guinea pigs,
          rabbits and human beings.
          The latter, ns weU as the rest, showed
          considerable Irritation under tho rays. We
          have reason to believe that certain plant
          and animal seed does not develop under
          radium rays; leaves lse their healthy, green
          color, etc
          I subjected the skin ot a, guinea nig, of
          a rabbit and a young man to radium rays
          and durlhg the first three days observed
          no change; on tho fourth dav the skin
          looked inflamed, a swelling appeared and
          finally an open wound of the kind known
          In. medicine as ulcus necrodlum.
          rn
          Ji.1 .III., In J
          This latter hu so far defied all attempts 1
          at healing.
          WHITE Mien DIED
          FOIl LACK OF BREATH.
          A most Interesting observation was mads
          on a dozen whlto mice, placed In a glass
          Jar -Kith liberal provisions. On the top of
          the Jar I put a small'box ot radium, en
          cased In pasteboard and metal.
          The mice enjoyed themselves for twlos
          twenty-four hours.
          After that they exhibited signs ot 41
          tress. lying .listlessly on their back On
          tbo fifth day all were dead,.
          Investigation proved that every one of
          tho-rodents died of paralysis of the breath
          ing ctntorB. "?;X
          Itadlum'e Influence) on the skin suggests
          that It may be a powerful aid of medicine
          m curing Biun oiseasea.
          Several of my medical friends, are exper
          menting on, the lines Indicated, and on
          Lupus tho results eo far have been very
          encouraging.'
          Another Interesting fact: I subjected the
          unfmctilled egg cell of a lower animal to
          radium rays, .and It began to develop.
          In the case of rabbits I observed that
          their coat Improved on the Bide subjected
          to radium rayft. In short, I am all together
          hopeful that radium may do for us many
          things heretofore considered Impossible.
          Too bad that It Is bo scarce and expensive
          as to be without reach for the poor blind
          especially.
          Perhaps the State will help them, now
          that their futuro begins to look bright.
          I certainly think that the blind man's
          chances for getting back his sight, or ac
          quire It, hae unmeasurcably Improved
          since the discovery ot radium.
          In this respect let no one be discouraged
          by reports of experiments that failed.
          Those described by the writer were aa
          tlrely successful, and the minutes of the
          case axe at the disposal of all Interested.
          Eye specialists of all nations should at
          once begin experimenting with radium.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-12-27/ed-1/?sp=29&q=Radium+Effects+Marie+Pierre+Curie+Metal+Experiment&st=text&r=0.142,1.045,0.233,0.352,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text> EXPERIMENTING WITH RADIUM UPON ANIMALS. Photograph taken especially for Th« Tribune
          by Harry C. Elus, of Paris, showing Professor M. J. Danysz in hta laboratory at the
          Pasteur Institute there, who is conducting an investigation Into the effects of the new
          metal upon life. RADIUM'S EFFECTS ON ANIMAL LIFE. The Metal Arrests Growth of Microbes, as
          Shoivn by Experiments Now Going On in Paris. Paris. December 17. Radium, that precious
          ni^tul discovered by the joint research's of Professor Pierre Curie, of the scientific
          faculty Of the Sorbonne, and his wife, and of which only five grams have ever been
          obtained, becomes more mysterious arid phenomenal with each successive scientific
          Investigation. It was Mme. Curie who, by her own experiments, first succeeded In isolating
          radium and olkcting it in the form of a pure salt From ten tons of pitchblende. LroUKht
          from Joacbinstal. in Bohemia, two de.i grams of radium were extracted after a long and
          delicate chemical process. The cost of ob taining radium was estimated last year at
          LSO.OOO franca, or MJOO. a gram. This would be at the rate of 150,0U0.<-HA> francs, or $30,
          000.000, a kilogram. I called upon Mme. Curie at her quaint little house, near Montsouris
          Park, the other day. Her husband had gone to London to attend a scientific meeting. I
          asked Mme. Curie if she had any additional revelations to make regard ing the
          extraordinary metal which perplexes FOUNDATIONS OF THE LOUVRE. "SKtrsr jrar-a asawatf rs
          bs-bs burled out of sight for two hundred years. and balMes the scientific world and which
          defies all the hitherto accepted laws of physics. Mme. Curie replied that in addition to
          the exhaustive paper that her husband read before the Royal Institution of Great Britain
          on June 19 last there had been no further important develop ments to disclos?. Mme. Curie
          is a woman of a purely and thoroughly scientific temperament. She positively declined to
          be drawn out into any expression of opinion or conjecture in re gard to any of the
          practical results or benefits to humanity that may eventually be obtained from radium. She
          refused, for instance, to say whether she thought that radium might some day stive as a
          cure or prevention of cancer. In response to such questions Mme. Curie simply said: "Why,
          I do not know. How can I tell? I am not aware that anything in that di rection has been
          actually demonstrated!" Sir William Ramsay's announcement that radium gives off a heavy
          gas, which slowly changes into helium and then vanishes, was mentioned, but Mine, Curie,
          with cast iron devotion to truth, would not venture upon any assertion not supported by
          absolute scientific demonstra tion. In reply to my question "whether efforts were being
          made to procure radium in larger quantities than heretofore," Mme. Curie replied "that the
          Austrian government was taking pos session of the pitchblende deposits In Bohemia, which
          were by no means inexhaustible, and tha result of this would be that the future cost of
          obtaining radium would be very much greater, than hitherto— perhaps twice as much." This
          would put the price of radium at $GO.OOO,OO<> a kilogram. The fact is of great importance
          in connection with the statement made to me last spring by Professor Curie, who said that
          the probability of extracting radium under favorable conditions from the pitchblende
          deposits in Col orado was most promising. 1 asked Mme. Curie what experiments just now
          going on In Paris were of the greatest in terest. The emphatic reply was: 'By all means
          those conducted at the Pasteur Institute by BL J. Danysz, who is investigating the
          pathogenic action of rays and emanations emitted by radium upon various animal tissues and
          sub stances."
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn89066489/1904-05-12/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Radium+Liquid+Sunshine&st=text&r=-0.359,-0.086,1.717,1.717,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Tbeir glasses, charged with "liquid
          sunshine." and facing a tanner behind
          the to&stmaster. hich gios-td viih M.
          T.," the truest at the annual dinner ot
          the Technology dub, held at the Univer
          sity clubhouse, at New York, the other
          night, rose in the dark and drank to their
          alma mater, the Massachusetts Insti
          tute of Technology. Radium made the
          "liquid sunshine cocktails" luminous,
          and radium paint prepared by Lester D.
          Gardner illuminated the banner and
          later played a leading parr in the series
          of experiments under the title of "hav
          ing a little fua with science.'
          No attempt was made to Introduce
          any of the new wonders of radio activ
          ity, but Mr. Gardner had prepared a se
          ries of entertaining demonstrations of
          what caa be done with radium In the
          way of amusing spectators. The "liquid
          sunshine." whkh as drunk without any
          apparent disturbance of the diner's di
          gestive organs, was the novel feature
          of a dinner which had many surprises.
          Mr. Gardner explained the co mix
          tion ot his novel drink. A portion ot
          esculln fluorescent chemical was dis
          solved In each glass of water. In the
          glass was s tiny tube containing a mi
          nute portion of radium. The radium,
          acting on the esculio, caused the con
          tents of the glass to glow in the dark
          ness. Then there appeared In the dnrlnes
          a skeleton Jumplcg-Jar!;. which waved
          Its arms and legs and wacgled its head.
          In another part of the room uriilinly
          appeared a second skeleton, which re
          mained motionless, but sufficiently
          ghostlike to frighten an unwarned au
          dience. The luminosity of these and
          other toys which Gardner Introduced
          Mas explained In a llv.ie speech. Mr.
          Gardner said: "I now call your atten
          tion to radium paint, so-called; this Is
          merely a raw form of cur eld friend,
          luminous paint."
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86063539/1910-03-25/ed-1/?sp=8&q=Edison+Puzzled+Radium&st=text&r=-0.292,-0.079,1.584,1.584,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          EOISON 15 PUZZLED
          (Vizard Of ElOOtrlClty FIndS Radl-
          urn's Secret Hard to Solve.
          Says fuel Is One of the Big Problems
          of the Future Talks of the Com
          Ino Air Machines and
          Future Food.
          Now York. Thomas A. Edison has
          been tnlking about somo ot tho won
          dors nnd problems which mako thts
          old world such an interesting placo
          In which to live. Hndlum, for In
          stnnco, moves him to enthusiasm, tho
          greater perhaps bocauso oven Rdlson
          lilmsolf hnsn't got on confidential
          terms with tho substnnco.
          Ha has somo at It, though. Oh, yes.
          Says ho: "I linvo a nplnthnrlscopo,
          which Is a tiny bit of radium, ot n slzo
          that will go through tho eyo of a noo
          dle, mounted ovor n ploco of wlllcmlto.
          It has boon shooting oft millions of
          sparks for tho six yenrs that I havo
          had It, nnd I expect It will bo shoot
          Ing spnrks tho samo wny for tbous
          nndfl of yenrs.
          "While only smnll quantities of ra
          dlum hnvo been Isolated, It exists
          overywhero In water, rock and soil
          Tho possibility of harnessing this
          forco for our uso Is somewhat ot a
          speculation. A radium clock has boon
          mndo and It will go sovornl hundred
          yenrs without winding.
          "Tho problem of fuel Is ono ot tho
          big problems ot tho future. Wo may
          find out tomorrow how to got nil
          tho power from our fuol wo got only
          16 to 20 per cent, now and on tho
          other hand It may toko a long time. I
          Wnter power Is being rapidly devel
          oped. Mnybo tho, utilization of tho
          tides will follow. Moro practical aro
          windmills connected with storago bat
          torlcs to lay up tho energy of tho
          winds In electrical form.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038615/1913-10-26/ed-1/?sp=57&q=Miracles+Medicine+Radium+Gamma+Rays&st=text&r=-0.194,-0.069,1.388,1.388,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          WREN radium was originally
          discovered public Interest
          was greatly excite by the
          merely curious properties of this
          substance -Its power of emitting In
          visible rays which penetrated solid
          substances, of rendering various
          bodies phosphorescent, taking photo
          graphs In the dark, of expending en
          ergy without apparent loss and so
          forth.
          Then came the discovery that ra
          dium possessed certain curative
          powers. The first results were not
          very convincing.' and popular inter
          est waned.
          Now, we learn suddenly, that
          physicians and scientists have for
          several years been patiently con
          ducting experiments which finally
          prove that in radium we possess the
          most wonderful curative agent In
          disease ever discovered.
          Radium has cqred many malignant
          growths which''were hitherto hope
          less. It has brought back destroyed
          body cells to life, It has exercised a
          beneficial effect in diseases of the
          liver and lntestlner?. nnd It Is now
          even said to bafillng disease, hardening of the ar
          teries'.
          In the early days of radium the
          effects of treatment were very con*
          tradlctory. Sometimes a marked
          aggravation of the disease was ob
          cerved, sometimes the radium pro
          duced serious Injury on healthy tis
          sue. But in many cases there was a
          surprising and unaccountable cure
          of a malignant gTowth.
          The reasons of this uncertainty
          are now understood. Radium emits
          three kinds of rays," which have very
          different properties. It also emits
          emanations, but that is another
          story. The three kinds of rays arS
          called alpha, bets and gamma rays,
          after the first three letters of the
          Greek alphabet.
          The most distinguished scientists
          In the world, including Madame
          Curie, the discoverer of radium, Sir
          William Crookes, Sir William Ram
          say, Professors Soddy and Ruther
          ford as well as many physicians and
          surgeons have been absorbed in the
          task of studying these three kinds
          of rays and establishing the differ
          ences between them.
          The alpha rays are the shortest,
          having a length of about an -Inch!
          They have a destructive effect on
          healthy tissue. That -was why, In
          early experiments, radium often
          caused such Injury. The beta ravs
          came next in length. They are about
          an inch nnd a half long. They have
          a stimulating effect on cell growth.
          They are, therefore, very dangerous
          when applied to cancers and abnor
          mal growths, but they are useful in
          other ways.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85053157/1914-03-04/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Wonder+Workings+Medical+Radium+Experiments&st=text&r=-0.286,-0.079,1.572,1.572,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          United States Has
          Now a Radium
          Institute.
          BY MEDICAL WORLD
          Scientists Are Busy
          Conducting Novel
          Experiments.
          1
          R
          i ADIUM. radium—more radium!
          This is the latest cry of the
          surgeon, for the curative pow
          er of radium, especially for
          cancerous growths, is now exciting the
          medical world. But radium is ex
          tremely scarce and wonderfully valua
          ble. Gold can scarcely be called a
          precious metal in comparison. Gold is
          worth but $20 an ounce, while a simi
          lar quantity of radium would com
          mand the vast sum of $4,000,000.
          What is more, there is every proba
          bility of the price of radium rising
          higher if some of the beneficent work
          it has already done proves to be last
          ing. Reference is made to what it has
          accomplished so far in battling with
          sinister cancer and to what it has
          wrought toward a return to health in
          lesser maladies.
          Radium fetches today at least $120,
          000 a gram, and the world over during
          the last year probably not more than
          a total of sixteen grains were extract
          ed from the hundreds of tons of raw
          material worked for that purpose. Of
          this amount about three-fourths had its
          origin in the United States, and yet
          today relatively little of this new found
          curutive agent is in the possession of
          American hospitals, physicians and
          laboratories. Foreigners draw the vast
          bulk of the mother substance from
          the mines in this country.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024827/1918-09-08/ed-1/?sp=7&q=Radium+Paint+Scarce&st=text&r=-0.185,-0.068,1.369,1.369,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          RADIUM
          MAY
          SOON
          New Yorks Latest Successes-Pretty Girls-Class Costumes
          OWN JASS ORCHESTRA
          Change of Program Wednesday and Thursdays.
          BE MORE SCARCE!
          Everything New But the Pretty Girls
          IN
          REV EW WANT ADS BRING
          RESULTS.
          A shortage of radium was forecast
          t-.y Dr. Richard B. Sloore of the United
          .States bureau of mines in an address
          I he deiivc red at Cripple Creek, Colo,
          Wednesday, before the annual meet
          !in of the American Institute of Min
          ing Engineers. Radium is largely be-'
          i in-, use J on the faces of watches and
          clocks and other similar purposes,
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030273/1920-05-30/ed-1/?sp=76&q=Radium+Rarest+Element+Danger&st=text&r=-0.253,-0.075,1.507,1.507,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          Radium Becoming
          a Household Aid
          Rarest Element Adaptable in Scores of Ways
          to Eliminate Danger arid Inconvenience
          of Groping in the Dark
          By DORIS' E.
          RADIUM, tho rnrest clement In the
          world, la rapidly becoming an r
          tlclo of ordlniry housohold use. It
          Is the most valuable metal .in tho world
          ono gram, which Is ono-twcnty-clghth of
          an ounce, costing $120,000 yet It Is used on
          more than four million watches nnd on In
          numerable 25 cent Indicating tacks. It Is
          so powerful that if any ono1 were to. .live In
          the same room with one pound of It the
          flesh would be torn from his bones. But
          there Is not a nound of It in existence, and
          If there were It would not exist In such
          rorm. Ynt despite Its power nnd value,
          children soon will play with its by-products
          ns toys, while their elders use It In a hun
          dred different ways.
          There Is more than uno youngster already
          who will not go to sleep nt night without
          having his pet bear with radium eyea beside
          him. And corners of rocking chnlrs will
          shine out warningly nt night, poison bottles
          vll' glow In the dark of the medicine cest,
          night marksmen will sight their rifles by
          the aid of it, mariners will riu'. more safely
          because of It and the late returning house
          holder will 1)0 able to find his keyhnlo moro
          readily in Its light. Motorists, miners, fish
          ermen, theatregoers, hospital orderlies, trav
          elling salesmen and what Is generally
          known as the great public will use this
          rarest of substances as casually as they
          wind their watches.
          In MilU and Mines.
          ilow much commercial progress Is to, owe
          ,o radium can be measured by Its rapidly
          'ii'Teaslng use In fnctorles. mills and other
          plants. Many mining corporations have
          adopted radium danger signals and guiding
          arrows. Radium indicators are not affected
          by atmospheiii oniiillon.s in i ic ulni
          whlch would make gas, oil and electric
          lamps useless. As long as there is darkness
          radium is visible. And In addition danger
          of explosion Is minimized.
          The tr.nrlner has already discovered many
          invaluable uses for radium. Especially is
          this true in tho case of the man nt the
          wheel. Electric lights, oil and gas are dis
          turbed by sudden motions and by the cut
          ting off of current or breaking of contacts,
          but when the compass card Is Illuminated by
          radium Its visibility is reliable. In the en
          gine nom, too, the telegraph control ist
          serviceable on foggy nights and In times of
          emergency.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn99065839/1921-08-19/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Radium+Mine+Hospital+Marie+Curie&st=text&r=-0.36,-0.086,1.721,1.721,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          OHN DICKINSON SHERMAN, i
          ONCERNING Mme. Marie
          Curie and her discovery
          of radium, her recent
          visit to the United States
          and the presentation to
          her by American ,omen
          of a gram of radium In
          recognition of her serv
          ices to science and hu
          manity the reading pub-lie-
          is sufficiently in
          formed. But where this American radium
          came from and how it was produced
          la another story, which may profitably
          be told In this connection. It is espe
          cially Interesting, Inasmuch as the to
          tal world's supply of radium Is esti
          mated at only 140 grams (a gram Is
          one twenty-eighth of an ounce). The
          Illustration by comparison sshows how
          small is this amount. The lower sec
          tion represents that made by the prin
          cipal American radium refinery,, the
          dark section that made by ther Amer
          ican refineries and the upper layer
          that produced abroad. So, though
          radium was not produced in the Uni
          ted States till 1913, this country now
          has made about five times as much as
          the rest of the world.
          Whue Mme. uurie, Dy aiscuvenus
          radium, introduced a new conception
          Into the fundamental problems, of ex,
          istence, she actually produced very lit
          tle radium, since she was denied the
          ores with which to work. Moreover,
          she gave It all away to the medical
          profession of Europe. A very small
          portion found its way to New York.
          In 1911 the late Joseph M. Flannery
          of Pittsburgh, who had made a success
          "with vanadium as an alloy for steel,
          devoted his attention to the produc
          tion of radium. The ores of other
          countries being out of the question,
          he turned to the carnotite deposits
          of southwestern Colorado, Prior to
          the World war this carnotite ore had
          been shipped to French and German
          producers of radium.
          Thfr mining' and handling of carno
          tite ore In southwestern Colorado Is
          attended with difficulties. The region
          Is desolate and practically uninhab
          ited. Water Is scarce. Flannery had
          his troubles. He had to train new
          men. He finally established headquar
          ters at the only spring of clear water
          within 100 miles; here the Standard
          Chemical company maintains all the
          offices for Its mining work, transporta
          tion and supplies. Eighteen miles
          away the company built the largest
          radium concentration mill in the
          world, through "which has- passed the
          ore from which has. been refined more
          than balf the world's supply of radi
          um. Burros carry the ores from the
          mines to the mill, and wafer and sup
          plies to the miners.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88074815/1921-04-08/ed-1/?sp=3&q=radium&st=text&r=-0.305,-0.08,1.61,1.61,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          that is to
          say, you might lose that amount if
          the little pile of white powder hap
          pened to be a salt of the metal radi
          um, but you probably will not need
          to worry; for they do not carry radium
          around in that careless way.
          They do not sell radium by the
          pound. One reason is that there is
          not a pound of. it in the world. An
          other reason i§ that there are not so
          many people in the world, even sinco
          the world has thade thi snew grist of
          millionaires, that could afford to buy
          a pound; for a pound of radium would
          be' worth around $50,000,000.
          Radium is sold by the ounce; the
          last quotation at hand is $3,360,000.
          Platinum, famed for its scarcity and
          value, is $l5O an ounce. Radium is
          200 times more valuable than the most
          valuable diamonds; it is 2,240 times
          as valuable as platinum; it is 180,600
          times as valuable as gold. A cubic
          foot of it would be worth $7,000,000,*
          too.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85042354/1921-04-22/ed-1/?sp=6&q=radium&st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          By Nrwepaper Enterprise.
          l'llTSBURGH Tucked
          away
          amid the manmoth steel mill* here,
          aa little known to Pitteburghors ne
          It 1* to the layman outside, la a lab
          oratory that turn* out seven-twelfth*
          of the world's supply of radium.
          The laboratory has been operating
          During nine years it
          since 1912.
          has produced Juat 19.9 grams of
          radium.
          And a gram la not quite
          a thimbleful.
          But these *8.6 grama of the preci
          ous metal represent a market value
          of 810,632,000.
          $3,500,000 an
          gram. It usually Is sold In Jots of a
          milligram, or one-thousandth part of
          Radium sells at
          ounce—$120,000 a
          a gram.
          But the Standard Chemical Co.,
          realizes only a nominal profit For
          every gram of radium that Is refined
          500 tons of ore and 1000 tons of coal,
          chemicals and water are consumed.
          Mining and milling forces also must
          be manlalned and high-salaried lab
          oratory experts paid.
          Radium was discovered In 1898
          by Madame Curie,
          she was the wife and former pupil
          Born In Poland
          of a French professor. Pierre Curie,
          who assisted his wife In her research
          work.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn96027122/1918-09-04/ed-1/?sp=1&q=radium&st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          SHORTAGE OF RADIUM
          Was Forecasted by Dr. Moore in an Address at Cripple
          Creek, Toda>; Radium Has a Most Decided Use
          in the World at this Time
          Cripple Greek, Colo., Sept. 4.—A
          shortage of radium was forcast by
          Dr. Richard B. Moore of the United
          States Bureau of mines in an address
          which he delivered here before
          the anua! meeting of the American In
          stitute of Mining Engineers. Radium
          is largely being used on the faces of
          watches and clocks and other similer
          purposes, the speaker said.
          It is a great pity that our supply of
          radium is being disseminated in this
          manner,” said Dr. Moore. “But as the
          physicians and surgeons of the country
          are not purchasing radium to make
          the industry a financial success, it is
          natural that the manufacturers
          should take other moans of creating
          a demand. The day is net far distant,
          in my judgement w r hen we shall great
          ly regret the radium that has been
          lost in this way.
          “Radium has a most decided useful
          ness at the present time; nine instru
          ments used on airplanes have dials
          made luminous with radium paints;
          it is employed in the same manner for
          compasses and gunsights. The effi
          ciency of night firing, with both mach
          ine guns and artillery, has been great
          ly increased by the use of these lum
          ;nous sights. Other uses can net be
          specified, at the present time, in a
          public paper.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025316/1913-08-27/ed-1/?sp=4&q=radium&st=text
        </id>
        <rel>
          1
        </rel>
        <text>
          American Radium
          Interests
          By Frederic J. Haskin.
          I:l t tilli it l' rarrtl ildt Illllo t v\ lu-t
          aIble oif t.:tlrtil l l.Ltt t 't l$.. unt i ftllti
          c intlY has tit I..tpr Idnll d nly in 1i
          rop,. altth llhugl t lhlt lnitd States ih'sti
          larger silI'ti's of ralitin i- prodi ting
          iire lthilan illa y other C la nty. Vhlat hltis
          L ooi.l rt i lly Iit tt l lnrtid al t it to i:
          s rv'id il tll tiliiliea an i llin, 11as t .1Io l
          |tthrytt'it oil o hti lll tilt s .t i n V .t 's Illt
          A imnria.
          1llce. It i lrump en (1hat thill total ;niiVwnI
          sutIt ly in tsi' wrathl toulnay a.otiin'I tot
          tolly >i littltloss Il tit th an o lll rni, nl
          11tiI. Tlet t o ti1t 41 I( rodi irt ti a i rl r
          tr rtS110mil ;1will g t'ilti tlu' tin r 1 zeal
          jewels of o tyratnt. Arl this is thei
          st(INl 1f Stuff WI' e11te hootn Wmlli g
          Until last y lrar ;ill ot f i the radium- r,
          Oftlig ores mInined in this tiintrv I.utre
          shipped to ,.ulroli. All il1nv ltiy.ttison
          y iltlhe United Sallts iiniltr of mines
          ov l.l u top l this f t, and, i tl l l nt, tl
          tie., theill mor imp io rtant non thit tihe
          Anerican lsupply tot' ores was the gra.n.'t
          est in the world. Until the proso'.
          y.Plr no Amlrieili radiulm1 Wil, onl (th
          market and onVl lle' firlm in thisl ainsll
          try wai s nrtnlaly prdrclling it. .Within
          the past six lmonths thre(e hr la1th.
          ratorihs have ent red the fit hint
          the value o1f their product is as y.
          problematical.
        </text>
      </result>

      <result>
        <id>
          https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1917-07-31/ed-1/?sp=9&q=radium&r=-0.033,0.414,1.589,1.451,0
        </id>
        <rel>
          0
        </rel>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>